So, imagine being a young person today, needing a job, seeking a livelihood, ready to build a future, and opportunities are hard to find. Young people are also telling me that they're worried that they're not getting the skills that they need. And again, they're right. We are finding ourselves at a time in the world when the world is changing so fast for work. We're in the fourth industrial revolution. Young people do not want to be on the farms and in rural communities. They want to go to the cities. They want to learn future skills for future work. They want to learn digital technology and green technologies. They want to have a chance to learn modern agriculture. They want to learn business and entrepreneurship, so that they can create a business of their own. They want to be nurses and radiologists and pharmacists and doctors. And they want to have all of the skills that they'll need for the future. They also want to learn the trades, like construction and electricians. These are all the professions that a country needs, as well as the professions that have not been invented yet. And young people are also telling me that they're worried about violence. At home, online, in school, in their communities. And again, they're right. A young person can have hundreds of friends on social media, but when they need to find a friendly face, someone who can be there as their friend, to talk to, they do not find one. They face bullying, harassment and more. And hundreds of millions are facing exploitation and abuse, and violence. Every seven minutes, an adolescent boy or girl somewhere in the world is killed by an act of violence. And girls are telling me that they're especially worried about their futures. And sadly, they're right, too. Girls face prejudice and discrimination. They face early childhood marriage and they face life-threatening early pregnancy. Imagine a population of the United States. Now double it. That's the number of women who were married before their 18th birthday. Six hundred and fifty million. And many were mothers while they were still children themselves. One out of every three women will face physical abuse or sexual abuse in her lifetime. So, no wonder girls are worried about their futures. These urgent crises may not be a reality in your life or in your neighborhood. And perhaps you've had opportunities for a good education and for marketable skills, and for getting a job. And maybe you've never faced violence, or prejudice, or discrimination. But there are tens of millions of young people who are not so lucky. And they are sounding the alarm for their futures. And that is why UNICEF and our many public and private partners are launching a new global initiative. Young people themselves have named it. And it's called Generation Unlimited or Gen-U or Gen you. So, what they're saying is, it's our time, it's our turn, it's our future. Our goal is very straightforward. We want every young person in school, learning, training, or age-appropriate employment by the year 2030. This goal is urgent, it's necessary, it's ambitious. But we think it's also achievable. So we're calling out for cutting-edge solutions and new ideas. Ideas that will give young people a fighting chance for their futures. We don't know all the answers, so we're reaching out to businesses and governments, and nonprofits, and academia, and communities, and innovators for help. Gen-U is to be an open platform, where people can come and share their ideas and solutions about what works, what does not work, and importantly, what might work. So if we can take these ideas and add a little bit of seed money, and add some good partners, and add good political will, we think they can scale up to reach thousands and millions of people around the world. And with this project, we're also going to do something new. We're going to co-design and co-create with young people. So with Gen-U, they're going to be in the driver's seat, steering us all along the way. In Argentina, there's a program where we connect students who are in rural, remote, hard to reach mountainous communities, with something they've seldom seen: a secondary school teacher. So these students come to a classroom, they're joined by a community teacher and they're connected to urban schools online. And there is the secondary school teacher, who is teaching them about digital technology and a good secondary school education, without them ever having to leave their own communities.
Así que, imagínense lo que es ser joven en la actualidad, necesitar un trabajo, buscando ganarse la vida, listos para construir un futuro, y las oportunidades escasean. Los jóvenes también me cuentan que les preocupa no estar aprendiendo las habilidades que necesitan. Y de nuevo, están en lo cierto. Nos vemos envueltos en un momento a nivel mundial en el que el mundo cambia rápidamente en lo laboral. Estamos en la 4ta revolución industrial. Los jóvenes no quieren vivir en el campo y en comunidades rurales. Quieren vivir en las ciudades. Quieren aprender habilidades del futuro para trabajos del futuro. Quieren aprender acerca de tecnologías digitales y ecológicas. Quieren una oportunidad para aprender acerca de agricultura moderna. Quieren aprender de negocios y el mundo empresarial, para poder crear negocios propios. Quieren ser enfermeros, radiólogos farmacéuticas y doctoras. Quieren contar con todas las habilidades que necesitarán para el futuro. También deberán aprender oficios, para ser constructores y electricistas. Estas son las profesiones que un país necesita, tanto como las profesiones que todavía no se han inventado. Los jóvenes también me cuentan que les preocupa la violencia. En casa, en Internet, en la escuela y en sus comunidades. Y nuevamente, tienen razón. Un joven puede llegar a tener cientos de amigos en las redes sociales, pero cuando necesitan un rostro amigable, alguien que pueda apoyarlos como amigos, con quien conversar, no tienen a nadie. Enfrentan «bullying», acoso y más. Y cientos de millones son sometidos a explotación y abuso, y violencia. Cada siete minutos, un niño o niña adolescente es asesinado en un acto de violencia en alguna parte del mundo. Y las niñas me cuentan que están particularmente preocupadas por su futuro. Y, lamentablemente, están en lo cierto. Las niñas enfrentan prejuicios y discriminación. Enfrentan matrimonio infantil y embarazos prematuros que ponen en riesgo sus vidas. Piensen en el total de la población de EE. UU. Ahora duplíquenla por dos. Ese es el total de mujeres que fueron casadas antes de cumplir 18 años. Seiscientos cincuenta millones. Y muchas fueron madres mientras ellas mismas seguían siendo niñas. Una de cada tres mujeres deberá afrontar violencia física, o abuso sexual en su vida. Así que, no es extraño que las niñas estén preocupadas por su futuro. Estas crisis urgentes pueden no ser una realidad en su vida o en su barrio. Y quizás tuvieron la oportunidad de una buena educación, de habilidades útiles y de conseguir empleo. Y quizás, nunca enfrentaron la violencia, el prejuicio, o la discriminación. Pero hay decenas de millones de jóvenes que no tuvieron esa suerte. Y nos están alertando sobre su futuro. Es por eso que UNICEF y muchos de nuestros socios públicos y privados lanzamos una nueva iniciativa global. Los mismos jóvenes la nombraron. Se llama «Generación sin límites», o en inglés, Gen-U o Gen tú. Lo que nos están diciendo es que es nuestro momento, nuestro turno, nuestro futuro. Nuestro objetivo es muy claro. Queremos a todos los jóvenes en la escuela, aprendiendo, capacitándose, o en empleos acordes con su edad para el año 2030. Este objetivo es urgente, es necesario, es ambicioso. Pero también pensamos que es realizable. Así que convocamos soluciones innovadoras y nuevas ideas. Ideas que les den a los jóvenes la oportunidad de luchar por su futuro. No conocemos todas las respuestas, así que estamos pidiendo ayuda a las empresas, los gobiernos, las ONG, el ámbito académico, las comunidades, y los innovadores. Generación sin límites es una plataforma abierta, donde la gente puede compartir sus ideas y soluciones acerca de lo que funciona, lo que no funciona, y aún más importante: lo que podría funcionar. Entonces, si tomamos estas ideas y sumamos un capital inicial, y buenos socios, y buena voluntad política, creemos que pueden crecer y llegar a miles y millones de personas en todo el mundo. Con este proyecto, también vamos a hacer algo nuevo. Vamos a co-diseñar y co-crear con los jóvenes. Con Generación sin límites van a estar atrás del volante, marcándonos el camino. En Argentina tenemos un programa en el que conectamos a los estudiantes que se encuentran en comunidades remotas o montañosas de difícil acceso, con algo que ven muy raramente: un maestro de escuela secundaria. Entonces los estudiantes en un salón, con un maestro rural de la comunidad se conectan con escuelas urbanas a través de Internet. Allí tendrán el maestro de secundaria, que les enseña acerca de tecnología digital ofreciéndoles una educación secundaria de calidad sin que tengan que viajar fuera de sus propias comunidades.
And in South Africa, there's a program called Techno Girls. And these are girls from disadvantaged neighborhoods who are studying the STEM program area: science, technology, engineering and math. And they have a chance to job shadow. This is the way that they then can see themselves
En Sudáfrica, existe un programa llamado Chicas Tecno. Y estas son chicas que vienen de barrios bajos pero están aprendiendo disciplinas CTIM: ciencia, tecnología, ingeniería y matemáticas. Y tienen la oportunidad de observar profesionales. De esta forma, pueden verse a ellas mismas
in jobs that are in engineering, in science, and maybe in the space program. In Bangladesh, we have partners who are training tens of thousands of young people in the trades, so that they can become motorcycle repair people, or mobile phone service people. But these are a chance to see their own livelihoods. And maybe even to have a business of their own. And in Vietnam, there's a program where we are pairing young entrepreneurs with the needs in their own local communities. So with this program, a group gathered and they decided that they would solve the problem of transportation for people with disabilities in their communities. So with a mentor and a bit of seed funding, they've now developed a new app to help the whole community. And I've seen how these programs can make a difference. When I was in Lebanon, I visited a program called Girls Got IT, or Girls Got It. And in this program, girls who have been studying computer skills and the STEM program have a chance to work side by side with young professionals, so that they can learn firsthand what it's like to be an architect, a designer or a scientist. And when you see these girls, smiles on their faces, the hot lights in their eyes, they are so excited, they have hope for the future. They want to change the world. And now, with this program and these mentors, they'll be able to do it. But these ideas and programs are just a start.
en carreras de ingeniería, ciencia, y hasta quizás en programas espaciales. En Bangladesh, contamos con socios capacitando a decenas de miles de jóvenes en oficios, para que puedan ser técnicos en reparación de motocicletas, o técnicos en telefonía celular. Esto les da la posibilidad de valerse por sus propios medios. Y quizás de desarrollar su propio negocio. Y en Vietnam, tenemos un programa en el que reunimos a los jóvenes emprendedores con las necesidades de sus propias comunidades locales. Entonces con este programa, se reunió un grupo y decidieron que resolverían el problema del transporte para personas discapacitadas en sus comunidades. Y con un mentor y poco de capital inicial, desarrollaron una aplicación para ayudar a toda la comunidad. He visto cómo estos programas pueden hacer una diferencia. Cuando estuve en el Líbano, visité un programa llamado «Girls Got IT», o «Chicas en tecnología». En este programa, las niñas que estudian informática y el programa CTIM tienen la oportunidad de trabajar junto a jóvenes profesionales, para que puedan aprender de primera mano qué es ser una arquitecta, diseñadora, o científica. Y cuando vemos a estas niñas, la sonrisa en sus rostros, el entusiasmo en sus miradas, están emocionadas, tienen esperanza para el futuro. Quieren cambiar el mundo. Y ahora, con este programa con estos mentores, podrán hacerlo. Sin embargo estas ideas y programas son solo el comienzo.
They'll only reach a fraction of the young people that we need to reach. We want to take these ideas and find ways to scale them up. To reach more young people in more communities, in more places around the world.
Solo llegarán a una porción de los jóvenes que lo necesitan. Queremos tomar estas ideas y encontrar formas de ampliarlas. Para llegar a más jóvenes en más comunidades, y más lugares alrededor del mundo.
And we want to dream big. Could every school, everywhere in the world, no matter how remote or mountainous, or even if it's in a refugee camp, could they be connected to the internet? Could we have instant translation for young people,
Queremos soñar en grande. ¿Sería posible que todas las escuelas en el mundo, sin importar qué tan remotas, o inclusive en campos de refugiados, estén conectadas a Internet? ¿Podríamos tener traducción instantánea para los jóvenes,
so that you could get a good education in your own language, anywhere in the world? And would it be possible that we could connect the education in your school with skills that you're going to need to get a job in your own community? So that you actually can move from school to work. And more. Can each one of us help?
para que puedan tener una buena educación en su propio idioma, en cualquier parte del mundo? ¿Y, sería posible poder conectar la educación en tu escuela con las habilidades que necesitarás para tener empleo en tu comunidad? Para poder transicionar de la escuela al trabajo. Y más. ¿Puede cada uno de nosotros ayudar?
In our everyday lives and in our workplaces, are there ways that we could support young people? Young people are asking us for apprenticeships, for job shadowing, for internships. Could we do this? Young people are also asking us for work-study programs, places where they can learn and earn. Could we do this and could we reach out to a community that's nearby, that's less advantaged, and help them? Young people are also saying that they want to help other young people. They want more space and more voice, so that they can gather to help each other. In HIV centers, in refugee camps, but also to stop online bullying and early child marriage. We need ideas, we need ideas that are big and small,
En nuestra vida cotidiana en nuestros lugares de trabajo, ¿qué podemos hacer para respaldar a los jóvenes? Los jóvenes nos piden formación, pasantías, prácticas laborales. ¿Podríamos hacerlo? Los jóvenes también nos piden programas académicos de empleo. lugares donde puedan aprender y ganar el sustento. ¿Podríamos hacer esto y conectarnos con las comunidades cercanas, las menos afortunadas y ayudarlos? Los jóvenes también quieren ayudar a otros jóvenes. Quieren más espacio y más voz y voto para reunirse y ayudarse unos a otros. En centros de HIV, en campos de refugiados, pero también para detener el «bullying» y el matrimonio infantil. Necesitamos ideas, grandes y pequeñas,
ideas that are local and global. This, in the end, is our responsibility. A massive generation of young people are about to inherit our world. It is our duty to leave a legacy of hope and opportunity for them but also with them. Young people are 25 percent of our population. But they are 100 percent of our future. And they're calling out for a fighting chance to build a better world. So their call should be our calling. The calling of our time. The time is now, the need is urgent. And 1.8 billion young people are waiting. Thank you. (Applause)
ideas a escala local y a escala global. Al fin de cuentas, esta es nuestra responsabilidad. Una generación masiva de jóvenes está a punto de heredar el mundo. Es nuestro deber dejarles un legado de esperanza y oportunidades. para ellos, pero también con ellos. Los jóvenes representan el 25% de nuestra población. Pero son el 100% de nuestro futuro. Y nos están desafiando por una oportunidad de lucha para construir un mundo mejor. Y su desafío también debería ser nuestro. El desafío de nuestra era. Y el momento es ahora, la necesidad es urgente. Y 1.800 millones de niños y niñas jóvenes están esperando. Gracias. (Aplausos)